Preliminary Inventory to the New Jewish Agenda Records TAM.183
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
New Jewish Agenda Records
1980-circa 1992
TAM.183
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
41.0 linear feet (42 boxes)
New Jewish Agenda (1980-1992), was a progressive multi-issue organization whose members included secular and observant Jews drawn from many sectors of the Left. NJA had some forty-five local chapters and five task forces: Middle East, Economic and Social Justice, Nuclear Disarmament, Central America, and the Feminism (later to include AIDS) task force. NJA also sought to develop a progressive Jewish cultural and religious ethos, reflected in its creation of The Shalom Seders: Three Haggadahs (1984). The process-oriented, “participatory democracy” political culture of NJA complicated its efforts to deal with its infiltration, circa 1987, by the New Alliance Party, whose views were antithetical to those of NJA. The organization also faced hostility from mainstream organized Jewry for its critical view of Israeli foreign policy, ongoing financial difficulties, and the erosion of some of its membership to other, usually single-issue progressive Jewish organizations, and eventually disbanded in 1992. The collection contains national administrative records, including convention, national council and steering council records, including minutes, correspondence, internal bulletins, reports, mailings, membership lists, press releases, some officers’ records (for example, those of Rena Bernards and Anna Jaffe); fundraising, task force and chapter records (including extensive files on the Portland, OR chapter), issues of its national newsletters, Agenda, Agenda-in-Brief and Gesher (published by the Feminist Task Force), and printed ephemera produced by NJA and other progressive (especially Jewish) organizations. NOTE: This collection is housed offsite and advance notice is required for use.
New Jewish Agenda (Organization).
Arrangement
The collection is organized into four series:
I, Records
II, Portland, Oregon Chapter Records
III, Linda Erber Materials
IV, Tom Rawson Files
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Americans for Progressive Israel Records. (TAM #147)
Separated Materials
New Jewish Agenda Photographs. (Photographs #145)
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions. NOTE: This collection is housed offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
Gift of New Jewish Agenda, February 24, 1995, and of Sandy Polishuk and Harry Stein, 2006 (Portland, Oregon chapter records).
Historical/Biographical Note
New Jewish Agenda (1980-1992), aka “Agenda,” identified itself as “a Jewish voice among progressives and a progressive voice among Jews.” NJA was a multi-issue organization that included secular and observant Jews, Jews from the organized Left (principally the New Left of the 1960s-1970s), and politically unaffiliated Jews; it was organized into some forty-five local chapters. The political concerns of NJA were reflected in the names of the task forces through which the bulk of its activity was conducted: the Middle East Task Force (advocating a two-state solution to the Israeli-Palestinian conflict, and opposing settlements in the occupied territories), the Economic and Social Justice Task Force, the Nuclear Disarmament Task Force, the Central America Task Force (in particular opposing U.S. policy in El Salvador and Nicaragua), and the Feminism (later to include AIDS) Task Force, which reflected the strong presence of women and homosexuals in Agenda. NJA also sought to develop a progressive Jewish cultural and religious ethos, reflected in its creation of The Shalom Seders: Three Haggadahs (1984), and also devoted some attention to the issues of Soviet Jewry and Ethiopian Jews. The process-oriented, “participatory democracy” political culture of NJA complicated its efforts to deal with its infiltration, circa 1987, by the New Alliance Party, a political cult whose views were antithetical to those of NJA. The organization also faced hostility from mainstream organized Jewry for its critical view of Israeli foreign policy, ongoing financial difficulties, and the erosion of some of its membership to other, usually single-issue progressive Jewish organizations, and eventually disbanded in 1992.
Sources
Block, Ethan D. “One Voice Less for the Jewish Left: New Jewish Agenda, 1981-1993.” http://www.newjewishagenda.net/PDFs/onelessvoice.pdf)
Nepon, Emily. “New Jewish Agenda: The History of an Organization, 1980-1992.” Senior thesis, Goddard College, 2006, and related material (http://www.newjewishagenda.net/).
“New Jewish Agenda.” Wikipedia (http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/New_Jewish_Agenda). (March 2009)
Scope and Contents note
The collection contains national administrative records, including convention, national council and steering council records, including minutes, correspondence, internal bulletins, reports, mailings, membership lists, press releases, some officer’s records ( including those of Rena Bernards and Anna Jaffe); fundraising, task force and chapter records (including extensive files on the Portland, OR chapter), issues of its national periodicals Agenda, Agenda-in-Brief, Internal Discussion Bulletin, Internal Discussion Bulletin on Anti-Semitism, and Gesher (published by the Feminist Task Force), printed ephemera produced by NJA and other progressive (especially Jewish) organizations, one box of files of Linda Erber,(NJA National Program Coordinator, 1988-1992), and two boxes of Tom Rawson Files (Boston Chapter, miscellaneous national NJA files). NOTE: This collection is housed offsite and advance notice is required for use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
36 boxes of records were donated by the New Jewish Agenda in 1995. An additional 5 boxes were incorporated into the collection between 2003 and 2011. Most recently, a gift of correspondence relating to membership development was made in 2013. The accession number associated with this donation is 2013.034.
Bernards, Rena.; Jaffe, Annette.; New Alliance Party (U.S.).; New Jewish Agenda (Organization). Central America Task Force.; New Jewish Agenda (Organization). Economic and Social Justice Task Force.; New Jewish Agenda (Organization). Feminist Task Force.; New Jewish Agenda (Organization). Middle East Task Force.; New Jewish Agenda (Organization).; Polishuk, Sandy, 1940-; Antisemitism |z Soviet Union |x Foreign public opinion, American.; Antisemitism |z United States.; Arab-Israeli conflict |x Foreign public opinion, American.; Central America |x Politics and government |y 1979-; Circular letters.; Clippings (information artifacts); Conferences.; Correspondence.; Human rights |z Central America.; Human rights |z West Bank.; Jewish radicals |z United States.; Jews |x United States |z Societies, etc.; Jews |z Soviet Union |x Political and social conditions.; Jews |z United States |x Attitudes toward Israel.; Jews |z United States |x Political activity.; Minutes.; Peace movements |z United States.; Social justice |z United States.; United States |x Foreign relations |z Israel.
- Series I, Records.
  Note
  Box "TITLES" in quotation marks are from the trans-files in which the records were originally housed.
  - National Committee and Steering Committee minutes, meetings and mailings, 1980s (Box 1)
  - National Committee and Steering Committee minutes, meetings and mailings, beginning 1987, 1987-circa 1991 (Box 2)
  - National Committee and Steering Committee minutes, meetings and mailings, 1987-89; three folders from 1982, 1982, 1987-1989 (Box 3)
  - "NJA 1987-90": Conventions, membership survey 1990; New Alliance Party; other administrative, activities, and topical files., Undated, 1987-1990 (Box 4)
  - "NJA 1987-90" - National Committee and Steering Committee minutes, strategic direction meetings; Chapter Files, Providence, RI - Z, and Canada, 1987-1990 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous: much loose material, and unlabelled files, undated, 1980s (Box 6)
  - "File cabinet drawers 1-2, 1981-82": Council meetings, correspondence, membership development, "Conference" [possibly] founding conference; topical files, 1981-1982 (Box 7)
  - "File cabinet drawers 1-2, 1981-82" conclusion: includes Steering Committee 1982-83; Internal Discussion Bulletin on Anti-Semitism, “Awareness and Action, A Resource Book on Anti-Semitism,” "NJA 1985-86" [11"]: mailings, workshops, funding proposals, 1985 convention, 1981-circa 1986 (Box 8)
  - "NJA 1985-86" conclusion [11"]: National Committee correspondence, fundraising, task forces [Middle East, economic justice], 1985 convention; "Staff files, pre 1991": foundations [mostly reference material, forms, and some correspondence], contributions, thank you letters, 1985-circa 1990 (Box 9)
  - "Pre 1991 staff files": foundations [mostly reference material, forms, and some correspondence], contributions, thank you letters, circa 1982-1990 (Box 10)
  - "Pre 1991 staff files" [9"] - foundations, chapter handbook; "NJA 1980" [6"] - topical and administrative files [1980s] (Box 11)
  - "NJA 1980": Founding convention, December, 1980; Early newsletters; "Annette Jaffe's files" [11"]: Steering Committee, Task Forces, packets for events, Undated, 1980 (Box 12)
  - Financial; Serials [Newsletter, Agenda, Agenda-in-Brief] Conference and convention bulletins and brochures, including some draft versions and associated reference material, 1980 (Box 13)
  - Serials, conclusion; "NJA 1983-84": begins with "Direct mail proposal" folder, also includes elections, financial, G2 merger, fundraising, 1980 (Box 14)
  - "NJA 1983-84 conclusion”; Middle East Task Force, Central America; General correspondence, National Committee, Development, Fat file of chapter flyers, newsletters, etc., 1989, 1980s (Box 15)
  - Miscellaneous staff files, 1989-90 [11"]; National Committee meetings, mailings, minutes; National convention; New Alliance Party, Undated, 1989-1990 (Box 16)
  - Miscellaneous office files, including chapter activity handbook, Shalom Seders, Bay Area Arbitration, 1984 [Bay Area Chapter charter revoked for advocating aid cutoff to Israel, while national NJA policy was neutrality on this issue], Undated, 1980s (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous office files; "Miscellaneous staff files, 1980s": including the Advisory Board, 1988 report, “General Support Proposal,” 1989; Middle East Task Force, Thank you letters, A-K; Large donors, Undated, 1980s (Box 18)
  - Thank you letters, L-Z, General Support Proposal, other files [11"]; Middle East files, including 1983 Israel tour, Undated, 1980s (Box 19)
  - Membership, circa 1988, by Chapter (Box 20)
  - Middle East files: tours, 1986-87, settlement freeze, 1987 World Zionist Congress, Americans for a Progressive Israel; Middle East Task Force, 1980s (Box 21)
  - Middle East Task Force: mailings, press releases, Internal Discussion Bulletin, 1987-90; Some 1991 documents, 1980s-1991 (Box 22)
  - Middle East: Gulf War 1991; Middle East Task Force 1982 - 1989, 1982-1991 (Box 23)
  - Middle East / Middle East Task Force, circa 1983-88, including Middle East Task Force internal documents, 1983-84; Shalom network, Circa 1983-circa 1988 (Box 24)
  - Chapter files - Akron – L, Undated, 1980s (Box 25)
  - Chapter files [9"]: M - Portland, OR; Holiday services by NJA and others, Undated, 1980s (Box 26)
  - Press Clips [mentioning NJA], 1980s-circa 1991 (Box 27)
  - Central America Task Force, Undated, 1980s (Box 28)
  - Central America Task Force [10"]: correspondence, Nicaragua, sanctuary; Steering Committee; “NJA History" [begins with "Lease" file]; Miscellaneous administrative, activities, and topical files, circa 1984-88, Undated, 1980s (Box 29)
  - "NJA History" [10"]: "E" alphabetical file, including NJA elections, Economic justice, El Salvador; Miscellaneous 1985 files; “Rena Bernards’ files," [begins with "negative mail" folder, and includes "Platform," 1982], Undated, 1980s (Box 30)
  - "Miscellaneous 1985 [Rena] Bernards’ files": alphabetical by keyword, M – Z: contains administrative, activities, and topical files, including National Committee, Nairobi, nuclear weapons, and volunteers (Box 31)
  - Middle East, A - N [roughly alphabetical by keyword]: administrative, activities, and topical files, Undated, 1980s-circa 1992 (Box 32)
  - Middle East [8"] N - Z [alphabetical by keyword]; Disarmament / Soviet Jewry / Economic and Social Justice Task Force, [most material is ESJTF and Disarmament, little on Soviet Jewry], Undated, 1980s-circa 1992 (Box 33)
  - "Disarmament /Soviet Jewry / Economic and Social Justice Task Force," conclusion [11"]: mostly peace activity, ESJTF; Gesher [Feminist task force newsletter of NJA], Jewish Socialist, Undated, 1980s-circa 1991 (Box 34)
  - Jewish Organizations, mostly progressive: printed ephemera and/or correspondence with NJA [box is half full], Circa 1980-1982 (Box 35)
  - Middle East activities and Task Force, Internal Discussion Bulletin, 1982-1990 (Box 36)
- Series II, Portland, Oregon Chapter Records.
  - Portland Chapter: about half of box consists of envelopes addressed to Harry Stein; the box contains a “NJA History” envelope, chapter and national newsletters (Agenda), ephemera, including from other progressive organizations, and some correspondence, Circa 1982-1990 (Box 37)
  - Portland Chapter: about half of box consists of envelopes addressed to Harry Stein; the box contains chapter and national newsletters (Agenda), ephemera, including from other progressive organizations, and some correspondence, Circa 1982-1990 (Box 38)
- Series III, Linda Erber Files
  - Linda Erber Files, c. 1988- c. 1991 (Box 39)
    General note
    Contents description provided by Linda Erber (NJA National Program Coordinator, 1988-1992) follows:
    Carrying It On: National Conference Organizing Against Anti-Semitism and Racism (November 8-10, 1991, Philadelphia):
    Proceedings; Xerozes of speeches; Transcripts of taped speeches; Organizing papers including letters to panelists, workshop leaders permission forms, confirmation agreements (including Julian Bond and Grace Paley), panelist biographies; Various organizing papers, training packet; Conference booklet. Awareness and Action: A Resource Book on Anti-Semitism, 1991
    New Jewish Agenda (NJA) Chapter Handbook
    Draft Manual for Organizing National Conferences
    Resolutions and Notes, Platform
    Notebook with various task force organizing notes (1988)
    Jewish Womens' Committee To End The Occupation file (JWCEO)
    Central America Task Force Packet, 4/1989
    Discussion Bulletin on Zionism, 1986)
    Misc. organizing papers, pamphlets, bulletins, correspondence and notes
  - Audio and Videocassettes, 1991 (Box 39A)
    "Carrying It On" NJA conference, audiocassettes, 1991; Ron Young, speech, videoccassette. NOTE: this box is not stored offsite, as is the rest of the collection.
- Series IV, Tom Rawson Files
  - Boston New Jewish Agenda Chapter Records plus Miscellaneous National NJA Records (Includes Middle East Task Force), 1980s-circa 1992 (Box 40)
  - National New Jewish Agenda Records, Miscellaneous, 1980s-circa 1992 (Box 41)